Bristol Brass Company Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Bristol Brass Company Records.
undated, 1911-1982.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Bristol Brass Company.
133 linear feet.
MSS19970029
The Bristol Brass Company was founded as the Bristol Brass and Clock Company in 1850, the creation of sixteen industrialists from Bristol clock and Waterbury brass interests who hoped to profit in the booming clock industry of Bristol, CT. Although the company never manufactured clocks, only the brass mechanisms for the timepieces, it was many years before it changed its name to Bristol Brass Company. It was the largest employer in Bristol, with 375 employees by 1880. Its mainstay was the production of brass for automobiles. The company thrived during the years of World Wars I and II, making shell cases for the military. The post-war economy brought a change in the company's fortunes. The amount of brass used in automobiles declined swiftly, and foreign competition eroded the company's clientele. Bristol Brass closed its doors in December 1982, after 132 years as a major part of the Bristol economy.
History
The Bristol Brass Company was founded as the Bristol Brass and Clock Company in 1850, the creation of sixteen industrialists from Bristol clock and Waterbury brass interests who hoped to profit in the booming clock industry of Bristol, CT. Although the company never manufactured clocks, only the brass mechanisms for the timepieces, it was many years before it changed its name to Bristol Brass Company. Starting with only sixteen workers, the company had become the largest employer in Bristol with 375 employees by 1880. By the turn of the century, it produced a variety of goods ranging from lamps for railroad passenger cares, souvenir spoons, and sterling silver flatware.
During World War I, the company prospered as the mill worked around the clock to produce war materials such as brass cartridge cases, bullet jackets, shells, truck parts, and ship fittings. In 1915, a new rolling mill was built at the plant to accommodate this increased expansion and a work force that had grown from 300 in 1914 to 1,000 in 1918. The company, however, had severely overextended itself during the war years and it suffered from the drastic reduction in armament production and the recession that followed the Armistice. Deeply in debt, the company was forced to sell its spoon and cutlery shops to the American Brass Company of Waterbury.
The company rebounded from its slump and sales soared when it began making parts for the burgeoning automobile industry in the 1920s. It produced radiator tanks, tubing, and other parts used in automobile manufacturing. The company also updated its facilities to meet expanding demand. The manufacture of brass was put on an assembly line basis that increased production and reduced labor costs. New machines, electric furnaces (to replace steam-generated ones), and even scientific research laboratories were installed in this effort to modernize the plant.
The Great Depression marked the end of these boom years for Bristol Brass. By 1932, the company had laid off one-third of its workers and those still employed were working shorter weeks at less pay. The National Recovery Act codes of the New Deal allowed the company to turn some profit in 1933 and it also benefited from a modest recovery in the automobile industry in the late 1920s, but the recession of 1937-1938 again brought a downturn in the company's fortunes.
Only the increased military spending of World War II brought good times back to Bristol Brass. Its main product during the war was shell cases. Organized labor established itself as a permanent fixture at Bristol Brass during the war when the employees joined the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers. After the war, when many unions conducted anti-Communist purges, this union was replaced by the more moderate and less politically active Local 1500 of the United Auto Workers. Like many manufacturing companies, Bristol Brass struggled in the post-war economy. The amount of brass used in automobiles declined over the years and the brass industry soon became a victim of foreign competition. The disastrous slump in the automobile industry during the 1970s only further hastened the decline of Bristol Brass.
By the early 1980s, the company was on the verge of bankruptcy as a national recession and a general overall decline in manufacturing in New England diminished its profits. The company was deeply in debt and unable to pay its workers, which, by the Spring of 1982, numbered only 200. It closed its doors for good in December 1982 after 132 years as a major part of the Bristol economy.
Scope and Content
Records of brass manufacturing company of Bristol, Connecticut. Collection is not completely processed.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Brass industry and trade--Connecticut.; Clocks and watchmakers--Connecticut.; Bristol (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Brass.; Bristol (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Clocks and watches.; Connecticut--Business, industries, and trades--Brass.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Bylaws.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Lawsuits.; Speeches.; Resolutions.; Petitions.; Personnel records.; Inventories.; Stock certificates.; Deeds.; Albums.
Occupations:
Manufacturer.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the University of Connecticut by the Bristol Brass Liquidating Corporation on 30 December 1982.
Detailed Description
[Note: Boxes 1 - 20 are partially refoldered.]
- Series I: Records, undated, 1911-1982
  - Meeting reports; Financial records, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Memo & reports on employment & benefits, 1956-1958; 1968 (Box 2)
  - Meeting Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Meeting Reports, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Memo; Correspondence (air pollution), 1975
  - Memo; Correspondence, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Memo; Correspondence; Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - Memo (labor negotiations), 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - Meeting report; Memo (Profit-sharing plan), 1972
  - Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 8)
  - Memo & correspondence on negotiations & Annual Meetings, 1968-1974 (Box 9)
  - Memo, correspondence reports on negotiations, 1968, 1971, 1974 (Box 10)
  - Contracts; pension plan, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Report of Annual Meeting; newsletter, 1974
  - Memo; manuscript; reports, 1970-1972 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence; manuscript digest memo (Delta Metal), 1970-1976 (Box 13)
  - Security exchange (original register), 1964-1972 (Box 14)
  - Bylaw Amendments, 1953-1971
  - Report of Annual Meeting, 1974
  - Memo, report (pension plan), 1958-1966 (Box 15)
  - Agreement, contract, 1973 (Box 15)
  - Memo; publication on cases & legal issue, 1968
  - Memo; Manuscript report of tax patent, 1965-1968 (Box 16)
  - Annual Meeting Report, 1976
  - Memo; correspondence (Portion Control), 1968-1975
  - Report of director's meeting, 1973-1974 (Box 17)
  - Memo; report (negotiations), 1972
  - Memo; report; publication; correspondence (Air Pollution Commission), 1970-1972
  - Memo; report; manuscript (benefit & incentives), 1954-1965 (Box 18)
  - Financial statements, 1963-1980 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence; memo; report, 1980 (Box 20)
  - Report; memo of board meeting; marketing plan; Product overview; catalogue, 1977-1978 (Box 21)
  - Financial & accounting records, 1971-1982 (Box 22)
  - Reports; agenda; presentation; plan; memo; digest, 1976 (Box 23)
  - Report; accounting records; digest; memo; company brochure, 1978-1979 (Box 24)
  - Banking account records; pension plan; loan application, 1964-1978 (Box 25)
  - Files about Mill Products Corp. & Delta Metals, 1978-79 (Box 26)
  - File (memo; correspondence; catalogue, etc.) about Mill Product Corp. & Accurate Forging Company, 1978-1980 (Box 27)
  - Employee's retirement records, 1960-1979 (Box 28)
  - Financial Statements, 1962-1965 (Box 29)
  - Payroll records; manual; brochure, 1980
  - Pictures, undated (Box 30)
  - Report of forecast; memo; correspondence; receipts of pension; year-end compensation, 1980-1982 (Box 31)
  - Bankruptcy material, 1980-1981 (Box 32)
  - Financial report; retirement income plan; Grievance Meeting report, 1962-1963, 1974-1979 (Box 33)
  - Correspondence; payment records; ledgers; air pollution Materials; acquisition & mergers, 1960-1979 (Box 34)
  - Employee payroll records, 1970-1979 (Box 35)
  - Employee earning records, 1945, 1973 (Box 36)
  - Tax-return materials, 1955-1959 (Box 37)
  - Annual reports, 1963-1970 (Box 38)
  - Account book & correspondence, 1911-1920 (Box 39)
  - Retirement Plan, 1964-1965 (Box 40)
  - Nominal budget, 1973
  - Executive comments, 1974
  - Financial statements, 1976
  - Employee retirement and pension plan; report of investments, 1956-1976 (Box 41)
  - Retirement Plan, 1973-1981 (Box 42)
  - Financial statement, 1965-1975
  - Retirement Plan, 1959-1979 (Box 43)
  - Financial statements, 1964-1969 (Box 44)
  - Compensation & retirement plan, 1979
  - Long-term borrowing material, 1965-1970 (Box 44)
  - Insurance material; tax forms; Benefit Plan, 1970-1978 (Box 45)
  - Retirement / Income Plan; tax information; annual meeting report, 1967-1977 (Box 46)
  - Group Insurance/ labor distribution record, 1981-1982 (Box 47)
  - Employee payroll and benefits record, 1958-1977 (Box 48)
  - Pension & Profit-sharing Plans, 1977-1981 (Box 49)
  - Agreement; meeting report; memo; financial report, 1980 (Box 50)
  - Agreement; contract; stock certificate, 1976-1982 (Box 51)
  - Report of meeting; water-pollution hearing; agreement; machine purchase, 1963-1978 (Box 52)
  - Financial statements, 1973-1977 (Box 53)
  - Financial statements, 1979 (Box 54)
  - Pension memo, 1970-1974
  - Financial Statements, 1959-1963 (Box 55)
  - Financial reports, 1936-1963 (Box 56)
  - Personnel records, 1936-1963 (Box 57)
  - Personnel records, 1936-1963 (Box 58)
  - Retirement plan; Profit-sharing plan, 1956-1977 (Box 59)
  - Secretary daily record; first-aid report, 1977-1981 (Box 60)
  - Personnel records, 1977-1981 (Box 61)
  - Personnel records, 1977-1981 (Box 62)
  - Personnel records, 1977-1981 (Box 63)
  - Bankruptcy material; accounting books, 1980-1981 (Box 64)
  - Financial statements, 1978 (Box 65)
  - AAP report, 1980
  - Meeting report, 1979
  - Adjustment plan, 1981
  - Bankruptcy material; miscellaneous, 1983 (Box 66)
  - Unemployment return; miscellaneous, 1977-1981 (Box 67)
  - Payroll authorization & control form, 1977-1981 (Box 68)
  - Secretary daily records, 1973-1975 (Box 69)
  - Publication (Sounding Brass); annual report, 1953-1973 (Box 70)
  - Power contracts, 1955 (Box 71)
  - Insurance report; acquisition file, 1964
  - Financial reports, 1962-1963
  - Labor agreement (Union), 1960-1974 (Box 72)
  - Printing Plates, 1960-1974 (Box 73)
  - Printing Plates, 1960-1974 (Box 74)
  - Printing Plates, 1960-1974 (Box 75)
  - Printing Plates, 1960-1974 (Box 76)
  - Printing Plates, 1960-1974 (Box 77)
  - Acquisition Files, 1972-1980 (Box 78)
  - Compensation plan, 1974-1980; (4 files) (Box 79)
  - Miscellaneous, 1972-1980; (7 files)
  - L. Killen's correspondence, speeches; Digest, 1972-1980 (Box 80)
  - L. Killen's service award tallies, 1970-1980 (Box 81)
  - L. Killen's correspondence and memos, 1974-80
  - Report of Board of Directors' Meeting, 1972-1975 (Box 82)
  - Report of Board of Directors' Meeting, 1975-1977 (Box 83)
  - Report of Board of Directors' Meeting, 1977-1978 (Box 84)
  - Report of Board of Directors' Meeting, 1979-1980 (Box 85)
  - Tax records, 1962-1970 (Box 86)
  - Tax records, 1977-1979 (Box 87)
  - Accounting records, 1978-1981 (Box 88)
  - Salary register, 1972, 1977 (Box 89)
  - Accounting records, 1977 (Box 90)
  - Accounting records, 1979 (Box 91)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1977, 1979 (Box 92)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1978 (Box 93)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1979 (Box 94)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1977-1978 (Box 95)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1975 (Box 96)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1978-1979 (Box 97)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1977 (Box 98)
  - Salary register (monthly), 1978 (Box 99)
  - Weekly earning report, 1978-1979
  - Pictures, undated (Box 100)
  - Monthly payroll register, 1981
  - Weekly earning report, 1977, 1980 (Box 101)
  - Salary, payroll register, 1979 (Box 102)